Today on the podcast, I sat down with Brandon Mulvihill, the founder and CEO of Crossover
Markets.
In this conversation, we discuss the future of digital asset trading market structure
in the US and how the liquidity landscape is likely to evolve in the coming months.
I think you'll enjoy this one.
So without further ado, here's my conversation with Brandon Mulvihill from Crossover Markets.
Matt Walsh and Nick Carter are partners at Castle Island Ventures.
All of these expressed by them or the guests on this podcast are solely their opinions
and do not reflect the opinions of Castle Island Ventures.
Guests and hosts may maintain positions in the assets discussed in this podcast.
You should not treat any opinion expressed by anyone on this podcast as a specific
inducement to make a particular investment or follow a particular strategy, but only
as an expression of their personal opinion.
This podcast is for informational purposes only.
Brandon, well, thank you for coming back on the podcast.
The world has changed quite a bit since the last time you were on this podcast.
My pleasure.
I really appreciate you having me and very excited to have this chat in Crypto Spring.
Definitely.
For those who didn't listen to the first podcast, maybe we can just start with a quick introduction
and overview of what Crossover Markets is and how you guys came to start the company.
I'm Brandon Mulvihill.
I am one of the three founders of Crossover.
I act as the CEO.
In Crossover, what we've done is we've built the world's first ever execution only trading
venue for institutions, meaning we're not counterparty to trades.
In fact, we don't touch coin.
Professional participants transact on our Crossover platform and face one of our credit
sponsors, which I know we'll get into that concept in this chat.
We also are the first ever Crypto ECN in the space.
We think from a differentiation standpoint that the ECN delivers quite a few advantages
over the central limit order book that is pervasive in the space.
At heart, what we're up to and our goal is ultimately to become the industry's primary
market for price discovery and risk transfer.
That's certainly a theme that we really want to get into later in today's chat.
Awesome.
Well, I guess the first question is just everyone had plans for the election.
If there went one way, there's a certain set of plans.
If it went the other way, I guess that's the world we're living in now.
Maybe talk a little bit about that as an entrepreneur, how you guys were thinking about the regulatory
environment and what the world looks like now.
We thought it was going to be positive either way coming out of the election.
With kudos to you, Matt and your team and your show because we listen to the show regularly.
You guys had been talking about bipartisan support sometime maybe last summer, last spring.
We felt like things would be good, but obviously with a Trump win, we thought things would
be accelerated.
Coming out of the election, you just can't trivialize or understate how important this
is to the entire ecosystem and to the industry to give you some tangible pieces of what we've
seen.
Debanking has been a topic of conversation as of late.
I know you guys have been talking about it for years.
I can tell you from experience, again, we're a company that's in the crypto marketplace.
We don't in fact touch coins.
If you look at our balance sheet, it's simply dollars coming in and dollars going out.
Yet with that, it was still very challenging for us to get a bank account over the last
couple of years.
Within two weeks of the Trump win, you could name tier one bank A, B, or C and the inbound
was tremendous.
That's just one example, but institutional interest has been sky high where all of this
is coming from or in part is that there's a real expectation that the US is going to
come out with a regulatory framework, the two big chapters are stable coins and then
market structure.
This positive change and this appetite to welcome crypto in the United States where
the US can really be the leading player going forward, I think, has created all kinds of
momentum.
I can see for your business, especially, it's just a huge development.
We'd love to drill into that a little bit.
So, Saab 121 goes away, all of a sudden the banks now can theoretically enter.
What does that actually look like in practice for a bank to actually mobilize and get into
the space?
We haven't seen a ton of public announcements yet, but it's still early.
What's your sense of the progress?
I think the progress is tremendous.
The first piece for a bank to come into the space and do the things that they would do
in traditional asset classes is they need to get comfortable with touching the coin.
One statement I'm pretty confident making is the blockchain itself and the nuance around
custody are both innovations and they are new to financial services.
When we think and talk about market structure and crypto, I don't personally see anything
that's new.
I see a copy and paste from traditional finance.
For a bank, what does this mean is for them to get involved, they need to get comfortable
with the idea of touching the coin, which means they need to be very comfortable with
the custody piece.
Obviously, we saw a hack 10 or so days ago with the buy-bit news and so that obviously
provides some level of discomfort.
If you're a bank, you have to get very comfortable with cybersecurity and things of this nature.
Once you are comfortable, then everything opens up and then the opportunity not just
to custody but to trade crypto becomes very real.
We at crossover definitely feel pretty strongly and we've certainly had some conversations
that support this, that the banks are going to come into the space and they are going
to play a dominant role in market making and adding liquidity into the sector.
We think that's going to be positive.
Where SAP 121 comes in is SAP 121, basically from a cost-to-capital perspective, made it
prohibitive for a bank to even consider touching the coin and holding the coin.
With that basically being chucked into the garbage can, now there's a realistic expectation
that banks can come into the space.
We've seen, I think, Bank of New York and most recently Citibank and State Street have
gone on record saying that those two would like to custody crypto by 2026.
That really is the foundation for everything.
Once we know a bank is comfortable touching the coin, then it's reasonable to expect other
things to happen, notably trading in the space.
In terms of actually getting to market, if you're a bank and you haven't done anything
yet, how would you actually get this to market if you were in their shoes?
Would you sub-custody?
Would you go buy a custodian?
Would you buy an MPC team?
How do you think this will play out?
I think, personally, through acquisition, I don't think this is a big shocking statement.
M&A, in general, in financial services is expected to be up significantly.
I think in crypto, specifically, we're going to see a handful of IPOs here in the US later
in the year, which is great.
I think for a bank to get involved, I think acquisition will be one of the dominant weapons,
but also partnership, maybe two strategic investments.
I don't know that banks are just going to license technology.
I think they'll probably partner up with some of the incumbent players, whether they're
custodians or they're the actual infrastructure like a firebox.
We'll look to see partnerships and maybe strategic investments attached to those as a stepping
stone to acquisition, but I think ultimately acquisition is going to be the dominant tool
used.
I tend to agree and think that sub-custody maybe as a first step will be the step that
some of these banks take.
We talk a lot about market structure.
The market structure bill seems to me like it would be later this year, maybe early next
year, stablecoins coming first.
That market structure bill doesn't necessarily get into the bifurcation of exchanges and custodians,
but you reference the buy-dead hack and that really calls into question whether that's
something the industry should be taking a lot more seriously.
What's your take on just that bifurcation?
Should those roles be separate?
How do you see that evolving in the US market?
100%, they should be separate.
Especially when we think about institutional use cases.
Think about right now life from the perspective of a market maker.
You're a traditional market maker that's either involved in spot crypto trading today
or about to be involved.
I know Ken Griffin just made comments from Citadel a week or so ago that they're going
to get involved in the space.
From their perspective, if you want to trade in crypto today and you want to trade with
100 marketplaces, you're settling bilaterally with 100 marketplaces.
This is just terribly inefficient.
Cost of capital will never be higher in crypto than it is today.
We are very much champions of the concept of fungibility.
This is the idea that a market maker like Citadel should be able to trade across 100
destinations, but net settle with one player, which traditionally would be called a prime
broker.
We can get to the same point with the concept of clearing as well.
The dominant player in that space is a company called Hidden Road Partners.
Hidden Road Partners has launched an OTC prime brokerage business in spot crypto.
They launched it several years ago, and I think that's been growing at great pace.
To your point, you mentioned custody.
Another way to think about this is you're one of the largest asset managers in the world
and you want to trade crypto.
What you're normally used to in any other market is you're normally used to the idea
that you can go choose your custodian, and that might be typically a bank, but whoever,
so custodian A, B, and C, and then separately, you want to trade with a bunch of people that
might be totally different names than your custodian, and then you may want to prime
broker and net settle with a company, and these are all independent.
What you're after, normally what institutions are after is they're after the collapsing
of their fees.
They want to trade more and they want to pay less on a yield basis.
Because crypto was born in the retail space, retail customers and mid-market institutions
normally care more about simplicity, so they like the vertically integrated model because
for you and I, for example, when I open a stock trading account or I think about where
I have my crypto, I don't want to have a custodian and then a broker and then a trading house.
I want a one-stop shop for all of those things, but for institutional support, it's a mandate.
We need to separate custody, we need to separate clearing, we need to separate execution, and
from a regulatory framework, the reason that this matters is the risk profiles of the players
in each of those channels changes, and so things like capital adequacy need to be different,
the focus, the emphasis on certain rules need to be different for each participant, and
ultimately, there will be participants who actually play more than one role, but while
wearing different hats, they will have obviously multiple regulatory licenses to perform that
activity, so we think it's an absolute mandate within the market structure framework that is
coming.
If it isn't actually pushed in the regulation, do you think it's just the market itself will
dictate that those are the types of businesses that will succeed here because institutions
will be less comfortable engaging with the alternative?
Absolutely.
Two things.
One is institutional demand, and so when you hear Citibank and State Street coming out
saying, we're going to custody crypto, now go back to that asset manager example, where
do you think they're going to custody?
I think the banks are going to be one of the winners in that space, but again, when banks
think about trading, they want to trade across a broad spectrum of places, and same with
an asset manager, they don't want just one liquidity source, they need multiple for not
only best execution, but also to collapse spread and keep their cost bases down.
I think from a regulatory standpoint, and I should declare that I spent almost 20 years
in the foreign exchange market before coming into crypto, so I'm definitely biased to the
FX market structure, and FX was governed by the CFTC, and we are pretty assertive in our
view that we really do think that the right place for the market structure framework would
be with the CFTC for the reason that crypto crosses borders the way currencies cross borders.
One way we think about this is regardless of where an institution sits geographically,
when they go to buy Bitcoin dollar, they're buying the same contract.
This is true of Euro Yen.
This is not so true when you think about US shares, where your domiciled internationally
actually plays a role into the contract that you're actually engaged in.
We think the CFTC is the rightful place for where market structures should sit.
The reason this matters is we think that the CFTC, if you look at Mika, for example,
and for those listening in, Mika is the regulatory framework that the Europeans have put into place.
The easiest way to describe Mika is that it's effectively a copy and paste from Mifid.
They've done a wonderful job, and I think that we could do the same thing in the US.
I think we could copy and paste a lot of Trabfi framework, and specifically the CFTC framework
on spot currencies into the crypto world. We think the demand from institutions,
and what we already have in traditional markets, we think are good enough to put out a proper
framework in crypto. Really interesting to think about because the CFTC, I don't think they have
spot market oversight on any other modalities. It'll really be at first if it's kind, if it
goes in that direction. I started my career in retail foreign exchange. Similar to crypto,
this goes back to 2004, 2005, 2006. There was no regulatory framework, and it wasn't until the
Farm Bill of all things on page 400 or wherever was written. It was the Farm Bill that basically
gave the CFTC oversight on retail foreign exchange, and then the NFA obviously put in
the framework. The CFTC has done a really, really great job on its governance of the
stock currency markets, including the retail space as well. I think the one thing we do have
to highlight, it's really not a copy and paste from just one market. There's pieces you could draw
from equities that are happening in crypto, and I think a lot from the currency market
in terms of the way it behaves. It's also clear that there are obviously coins that are definitely
securities, and so that does feel like it would sit naturally with this SEC. Our expectation would
be if you're a venue like us, we would probably have to register and be licensed by the CFTC
to operate the venue, but then if we were to have certain coins that were on offer that would be
considered as security, then we might have to have dual registration. That's also something
we think about and talk about. From a customer experience perspective, I guess that would be
critical to not have to change platforms if you're trading a security token versus a commodity
token. It'll be interesting to see how that actually manifests itself to the customer,
because hopefully it would all just be in one kind of interface, you would think.
I think so. It's hard to imagine why it wouldn't. For the same reason, there are online brokers
where on the same interface, you can buy a cash equity. This is pretty popular in continental
Europe, for example. You can buy a cash equities. You can buy a futures contract. You can buy an
FX contract. You could buy what they call a CFD. More recently, you could buy crypto all through
one interface, even though behind the scenes, that data information is being sent to different
regulators for the specific roles that functions where you hold your licensing. I think that should
be pretty achievable. Again, I think that'll be driven by demand. Clients are going to mandate that.
No one wants to log out and lock back into something.
I would think so. Talk about the goal of being the primary market in the US. I guess let's just
start definitionally with what does that mean to you? How do you see that market evolving?
For us, this is mission critical. I think the best analogy to draw from here is to think about
a bank. A market making, trading business line at the bank, when they come in and trade spot,
where do they get price discovery from? Where do they think about risk transfer?
How are they deriving their prices? When they build up positions and they need to exit,
what is the leading venue or top two or three places they look at to exit that risk?
To date, what happens if, under our head, we have to name one venue that's primary market is most
certainly Binance, specifically due to the level of volume that they do daily. What impact does
this have on institutional users? Well, you can feel it in proximity. Almost every market making
firm in crypto has some presence near Tokyo. Why? Because Binance is in AWS Tokyo. This is
another indicator that Binance, it's reasonable to state that they're currently the primary market.
Our belief is that no retail broker or retail crypto exchange is ultimately going to be the
winner, the long-term sustainable recipe for primary market. Certainly, we don't know that
American banks are going to be opening accounts with Binance. This is fundamentally a retail
exchange from China. I just don't think that it's well-positioned or may even care about
themselves playing a role in primary market. One of the things that we think about is in crypto
today, every crypto exchange is operating in a vertically integrated model, which means they
have the customer captive. If you buy Bitcoin dollar with exchange A, you have to sell Bitcoin
dollar with exchange A. Once you buy, they're guaranteed two trades. You can't buy with exchange
A and sell with exchange B. What happens is when you look at their actual matching engine,
the actual vehicle, that is not the differentiator. That is not where the investment has gone at
these crypto exchange. They're focusing on the peripheral advantages, things like the credibility
of the institution, the safety of holding your coin as a custodian, maybe the interface itself on
the mobile app or the charting package. You're not going to see a crypto exchange advertising
how fast its throughput is or its speed of execution or the fact that it's sitting in bare
metal and not in the cloud. That's not what you see. On our platform, prospects were execution only,
meaning when an institution buys Bitcoin dollar on cross-ex, if 10 minutes later they want to exit
their position, they can do it anywhere else. They're not obliged to do it through us. What does
that mean? It means we're competing every second of every day to win market share.
When I say things like we finished 2024 with our first year of live trading and we can say 99%
of our orders were matched in six microseconds, we're processing over 7 billion quotes per day
using about 1.5% of our current technical capacity. When I talk about our ECN execution
advantages and when I talk about these things, they're not just words. I have to prove it because
every institution who's connected never owes us a trade. I have to win that business based on
spread compression and the way we think about market impact. We think that there's a strong
correlation. In order to be in the game for primary market, your execution venue needs to prove an
open warfare that you can win market share if you don't hold the client captive. If you can prove
that, then I think you've got a shot. We feel right now as one of the only, if not the only,
execution venue out there that can make those statements. I'll give you two other data points.
As we've grown volumes, we have generated revenue on every trade since inception.
We haven't built market share by cutting any corners. The second thing is we're one of very
few venues, I believe, maybe the only, but one of very few that charges both sides of the
transaction. We charge the maker and the taker. We said when we started the company that our system
and the way it behaves technically provides value to both sides. I'm comfortable now saying with
those two statistics side by side that I think we can qualify and back that up. We can charge
both sides because both sides see themselves getting a value. That's fascinating. If you think
about primary market and maybe let's just drill down to what the retail leg needs to look like
to be the primary market, this market in the US has really grown up with these vertically
integrated platforms, Coinbase and Crackin really being the largest. How do you see just overall
retail flow evolving in the US? I'd have to imagine that a big piece of that is going to be
retail brokers that aren't active yet. Curious how you see that part of the market.
To finish the thought process on primary market, go back to what Ken Griffin at Citadel said last
week. If I read it correctly, he said that Citadel is going to enter spot crypto and they're going
to start by pricing Coinbase and Binance. The question is, think about it from their perspective,
trade one. Trade one, they're going to make a price to Coinbase. What are they using to think
about what that price should be? What we're saying where the gap exists in the market,
because we could talk for hours about this, is whether you talk for five minutes or five hours
or five days, the punchline is that right now there is not many companies that are well positioned
to be in that race to be primary market. It is not a really well thought through concept.
Now to your question specifically about retail growth in the States,
all signs are extremely bullish. I think there should be a lot of reason for optimism.
Ultimately, consumers, all of us, I think we all benefit when there's competition.
When there's competition, normally prices compress. Matt, you'll remember a day when we used to pay
what was it, $14.99 and $9.99 to buy a stock and now it's free. I think that's a good example of
what happens when you get competition. Coinbase, the obvious leader, has done a phenomenal job.
You've got Kraken, California-based and looking forward to maybe some positive news they have
this year, which would be great. You've got Robinhood. Now you've got a traditional name like
a Robinhood who does equities. Q4, I think they put up $70 billion of volume and over $400 million
in revenue, something of that magnitude. So just unbelievable results. I think what's happening
is that traditional online brokers are seeing that and they're seeing not only their revenue success,
but Robinhood's stock is up five-fold since it was just a couple of years ago and it's being
driven because of their presence and the growth expectations of what they're up to in crypto.
And so it shouldn't be surprising to anyone that both Charles Schwab
and E-Train have now announced that they have plans to enter the space. Interactive brokers has
been in the space a little bit. I could see them maybe paying more attention. You've got traditional
retail FX brokers like Awanda that haven't really put a lot of emphasis on this tasty trade.
I think you're going to see a lot more online traditional brokers enter the space,
which in turn creates competition. And I think that competition is going to be
very positive for the consumer. And I guess the obvious question is, what does that mean for
the future of venues in the US? And a lot of ways it feels like maybe the race hasn't even started
yet just due to some of the regulatory overhacks. When we started the company, we've done a seed
investment round in a Series A and 12 of our 13 shareholders are strategic. And one of the first
questions people had was, wait a minute, on another venue, talk through your differentiation.
One of the things that we do is if everyone would just stop calling it a crypto exchange and
instead just call it a broker, it's a crypto broker, then it's easier to think through what's
happening here because these retail exchanges are in fact brokers, which is fine. And so
very good business model. And again, for all the points I just raised, I think there's
going to be a lot of benefits and improvements for the consumer because you're going to get more
brokers offering the service. But brokers are not in the business of competing for primary market.
They're not a venue the way I think of a venue. For example, if any of these crypto exchanges
called Hidden Road and said, we want to take our exchange and have you prime broke it,
not a DMA axis, truly where we now need to win market share solely on the merits of our technology.
And I've seen some examples of this. I don't think they'd go anywhere. I think they'd really
struggle with the central loan order book model and the slowness of the technology. I think they'd
struggle to play a big role. I'll give you two data points. Speed of execution. We execute in
six microseconds. And so people go, why does that matter? The fair answer is to a taker of liquidity
probably doesn't matter at all, especially for retail clients buying something on a mobile app.
They don't need to respond to six microseconds. They're not going to notice the difference between
micros and milliseconds. However, from the standpoint of a market maker, they now see on
Cross-X 300 to 400 price updates and the time Binance moves once. Are they more comfortable
showing us a more aggressive price? Of course they are because they can change their mind.
We also, from a throughput standpoint, everyone knows when you go on Binance,
especially if you're a market maker, the more you trade, you can get effectively a cheaper fee.
What people often don't talk about is the crypto exchanges struggle handling data.
They have a throughput where they basically say you can only send us so many orders per second.
Now, interestingly, the more volume you do, the more orders per second you're allowed to send to
them. Order throughput is directly correlated to getting a smaller spread. This is called
throttling. We don't force throttling. We allow makers to send us as much data as they possibly
can. Again, just like speed, why do we care? Because this is what compresses spread.
I think the conclusion that I'm trying to draw is this is the level of sophistication that a
venue needs to have to operate independently and win market share. When I look at that space of,
okay, how many venues are going to come into the US? I look at it through a different lens of,
I think from a broker standpoint, we're going to see a lot more brokers in the US,
and I think they're going to see a lot more competition. In terms of folks that are entering
our domain as a true marketplace, a true standalone venue, I definitely think we're going to see
increased numbers, but it's a much, much harder moat. It's a much more difficult thing to stand up
overnight. That makes sense, which leads to my next question is, how do you think about the large
exchange groups that are not in crypto today and how they're going to play the market?
When we started the company, this is one of our big thesis statements. We felt strongly that
traditional exchanges, and you can go right down the list, your CME, ICE, ELSAG, Deutsche
Bors, TradeWeb, a CBOE who's had a couple of starts and stops in the space, MIACS, there's
NASDAQ. You can go right down the list. We said from day one that these folks would come into
the space probably when there's regulatory clarity, and that when they come in this space,
they're probably going to do what they normally do. They're going to buy. They're going to be very
acquisitive. I started this podcast talking about debanking. The other thing we've seen,
at least from inbound traffic, banks and traditional exchanges are certainly sitting
upright in their chair. Absolutely, if they're not involved, they're all building battle plans
of how to get involved. Predicting timelines for exchanges is a little bit tougher. These are
large institutions, publicly listed. They don't work week to week, month to month necessarily,
but I think it's fair to say we're going to see traditional exchanges play a role in spot crypto.
And aggressively, I think we're going to see a couple by the end of the year, if not a few,
but if we expand the timeline to maybe first half of 2026, I think we're going to see at least half
a dozen traditional changes enter the space. That makes a ton of sense, and that would be very
bullish. If you look at what this market could be, are there any other regulatory barriers that come
to mind that we should be thinking about as an industry? One that I think about a lot is just
the Basel rules and some of the constraints that maybe the banks might be under for certain lines
of business outside of custody and plain vanilla trading. You're hitting on really the most important
thing probably, which again is related to the cost of capital. That can be very prohibitive.
And when you look at, for example, capital adequacy, the UK and European and traditional
financial markets have fairly long equations for how you come up with capital adequacy. The US
typically has a more straightforward program, so that's something to keep an eye on.
I think the two things I would say for this is that again, championing the idea of the CFTC
and the idea that crypto crosses borders, it's important to note that crypto is a global thing.
It's not domestic. It doesn't recognize borders. And so people like us and institutions that are
going to play a role in the space need to think about what it means to be regulated globally.
This comes, I think, fairly natural to folks that were in the FX industry, because if you're in FX,
you have to have a relationship with the GFSA in Japan and ASIC in Australia and the FCA in the UK
and the US regulators. But this is not a trivial thing, because the way that Mika frameworks
works may not be identical to what happens in Singapore or in Japan or the US. And so
I think that's the big topic is for people that are going to compete, they've got to compete globally
and they've got to think about what that actually means to their business. I have something much
more nuanced though for you that we can kick around. I think there's a potential for one big
shocker in the crypto space from a regulatory standpoint. And that is, in my experience,
when you look at the growth of retail markets, be it in equities or be it in foreign exchange,
normally what happens is there's some practice related to execution that's not quite right
or in the regulator comes in and figures it out and then it finds all the companies and
then they stop that behavior and then onward you go. In retail FX, the idea was positive slippage.
So all of the brokers on stop orders, clients would get negatively slipped, that's fine,
but on a limit order, if there was a positive slippage, the broker would keep it. So when
regulations spread in retail FX in kind of the 2005 to 2010 era, global regulators caught this,
they made examples, $2 million, $3 million, $4 million fines, and then that practice went away.
I think crypto has one big disease that should be discussed, which is the exchange model itself,
the central limit order book model, doesn't recognize liquidity providers and retail clients.
There's only customers, it's everyone's swimming in one swimming pool. And so what happens is you
have all these HFTs and market makers that are now in this pool. And so the question becomes,
if Bitcoin crashes, 40% right now is we're on this, who's getting out of their risk first?
Is it the institution or is it the retail client? I'm pretty sure I know the answer.
And I'm pretty sure it's really bad for the retail client. I'm sure if they want to exit
their position, they're going to get out at exponentially worse prices because of this.
And to me, this is an inherent conflict of interest that would be deemed unacceptable
in any other market. I think it's going to take a while, but I do think the Western regulators
are going to dig into that. I don't think that that practice is something that we should bank on
moving forward. And just the way that these native crypto exchanges have built themselves,
I think that that could be very, very problematic.
Would you classify that as a best execution standard for crypto? How would we actually
talk about that once that comes to pass? I absolutely think it fits within the
best execution framework. And notably, it's around the concept of a conflict of interest.
Regulators, as we know, we saw it in the Mika framework, I would expect it here in the US.
Normally, the first driver of their focus is aimed at the protection of retail consumers.
This is a practice that I think is fairly obvious is not to their interest. And it's not
something we see in other markets. When market makers price is all schwa for equities, you have
liquidity on one side and retail on the other. In retail foreign exchange, it's the same way.
You have liquidity on one side and you have clients on the other. And there's numerous retail
brokers in the crypto space that do operate that way. And those are normally traditional
online brokers who have come into spot crypto. And so they've got liquidity on one side of
their tech and retail on the other. There is precedent for doing it that way. But certainly,
this would fall under best execution and an inherent conflict of interest.
It would be interesting to see how that evolves because it's not something anyone's talking
about right now. But if this does start to institutionalize, there's no reason to believe
that all of the concepts that exist in other asset classes wouldn't just be brought to bear here.
That's right. Sometimes I get overly philosophical so I can spend hours. It's not nefarious. It's
not something that these companies dreamt up to create a conflict of interest at all.
But I do think it underscores that when you see a lot of the founders of the retail crypto
exchanges speak, they don't see themselves as a financial broker. They don't see themselves
as a Charles Schwab. They see themselves as almost like an Expedia.com. When they use the
word exchange, they're talking about it almost in those types of terms, not in exchange the way the
CME would talk about themselves as an exchange. I think for them, this would be alarming on one
hand and I think very surprising. I don't think it's something that people have really thought
through all that much. I think they just think that the way that this thing works operationally
is totally fine. Better to get a run of stuff like this so that the next version of Gary Gensler
doesn't get his hands on it and make everyone's life very difficult in four or eight years, however
long. We'd love to close it off with just a little bit of a refresher on crossover. It sounds like
you guys had a banner of 2024. What does 2025 look like in terms of plans? We now have 70
institutions live on the platform. We're trading around $3 billion a month of spot crypto volume
and growing. I think we averaged $1 billion, a little over $1.1.25 per month last year. We're
growing right now in the last, I think, three quarters, around 50% quarter on quarter volume
growth. As we add more institutional participation, we expect the volumes to compound. I went through
some of our trading statistics we're awfully proud about in terms of speed, execution, and
performance. We're going to do two things that we think are big. Number one is all 70 institutions
we've onboarded are internationally domiciled. In Q2, we're going to enter the US for the first time
and try to stick a flag in the ground here and really play a dominant role. We've got big plans
there more broadly and related to that. As we are going to be adding to our distribution team and
business development, we're bringing someone on out in Singapore. We're going to expand into Asia
while we're also trying to build out in the US. Most of our business comes from the UK and the
European area. We'll continue that with our London office. Geographical expansion is one.
Then the second thing is we're launching what I'm calling Cross-X 2.0. We have delivered a new
architectural framework. It gives us a lot of advantages, but the two I would drive that I'm
really excited about is one, advanced order types. We're going to be launching a series of Pegna
Mid or what some call Mid-Match. We're going to run a Mid-Match book. I think that's going
to be very powerful for certain players, HFTs, market makers, passive hedges from retail brokers
who think about things like market impact, who've got risk and they want to move it
to de-risk, but they don't want the market knowing that and reacting to them. We think that'll be
great and also custom order types so that advanced trading shops, if they have an idea of how they
want to express their view on our platform and they want to give us an email sound by almost
like a spec, we can actually build a custom order type intra-week, which we think will be pretty
groundbreaking. The second thing though that is one of the things I've been most excited about
in a long time is really what we can call advanced best execution practices. What we're doing is
we're launching our advanced best bid offer and our smart order router. What we look at when we
think about who is the best price? How do you get the bid and the offer? We look at price, size,
and time. This is normal. This is what most exchanges and venues would look at, but now what
we can do is we can overlay the historical data of fill ratio, response times, and market impact
of the market maker in real time. For example, if you come in your top of book but your response
time is very low or we see that you're not filling trades as much as we would like, there's a real
cost to that. The cost to your price is actually worse than what you're showing. What our system
does is automatically account for that. Where we get the home run ball out of this is we operate
right now in bare metal and Equinex LD4 in London and Equinex NY4 in New York. We're also currently
in the cloud in AWS Tokyo, and later this year we'll look to go into either TY3 in Tokyo or SG3.
When you do that, this is true in every other market, when you have multiple matching engines,
they are independent of one another. They have independent liquidity and no one has ever tied
these things together in financial markets. We're hoping to be the first. Our CTO, our third co-founder
Vlad Ryzen, who's a double PhD in math and artificial intelligence, we're going to use AI to
basically combine all of the matching engines to have one global matching engine. The relationship
here is if you look at something, for example, like response times, the latency between New
York and London is around 70 to 120 milliseconds, not low or not higher. We know that it's pretty
static over time. If you know this mathematically, then you can imagine there are moments in time
where a taker in our US engine might be better matched with a market maker from our London engine.
Having this SOR overlay onto our best execution allows us to eventually embed AI to combine
all of our liquidity globally, as well as the customer's credit. We think that's going to be a
home run. That's fascinating. We love to hear stories about crypto and digital asset firms
moving into the US, especially from American pro-hovers. It feels like a new day over here.
Night and day. Matt, you've been in the business a lot longer than us. We started fundraising in
our seed round. I believe it was one month before three arrows in Celsius went down.
We've only ever known crypto winner. This is the first time we've seen the sun is out and shining,
and we obviously couldn't be happier. I'm excited for you guys. Thanks again for coming on the
podcast. This was fun. My pleasure. I appreciate it. Thank you, Matt. Thanks for listening to
another episode of On the Brink with Castle Island. To find out more about Castle Island,
visit castleisland.vc. To listen to all of our podcast episodes, please go to onthebrink-podcast.com
or just click on the tab in our website. Thanks for listening.